Guide to the Joseph Brodsky Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Writings, circa 1959-2000; Series II; 33.99; (86 boxes)
  - Poetry
    - Individual Poems
      - To the President-Elect, draft and printed version, 1992 (Box 67, Folder 1694)
      - Tomas Transtremer za roialem, drafts, [1993] (Box 67, Folder 1695-1696)
      - "Topilas' pech'. Ogon' drozhal vo t'me"
        - Russian language version, drafts, 1963 (Box 67, Folder 1697)
        - English translation by unidentified translator, draft, undated (Box 67, Folder 1698)
      - Törnfallet, drafts and printed version, [1990]-1994 (Box 67, Folder 1699)
      - Tors
        - Russian language version, draft, 1973 (Box 67, Folder 1700)
        - English internlinear by unidentified translator, undated (Box 67, Folder 1701)
        - English translation by Howard Moss, printed version, 1978 (Box 67, Folder 1702)
      - Torso
        See: Tors
      - Transatlantic, drafts, proof and printed version, 1992 (Box 67, Folder 1703)
      - Tri rytsaria
      - Tristia, by Osip Mandelshtam, English translation by Brodsky, draft and printed version, undated (Box 67, Folder 1704)
      - Triton, drafts, [1994] (Box 67, Folder 1705)
      - Tsvety, drafts, [1990] (Box 67, Folder 1706)
      - Twenty sonnets to Mary Queen of Scots
        See: Dvadtsat' sonetov k Marii Stiuart
      - "Ty, gitaroobraznaia veshch' so sputannoi pautinoi"
        - Russian language version, draft, 1978 (Box 67, Folder 1707)
        - English translation by Brodsky, draft, 1978 (Box 67, Folder 1708)
      - "Ty ne poimesh' etikh strok i naizust' uzhe," drafts, undated (Box 67, Folder 1709)
      - "Ty ne skazhesh' komaru," draft, [1991] (Box 67, Folder 1710)
      - "Ty pila zdes' u stoiki kholodnoe moloko," drafts, undated (Box 67, Folder 1711)
      - "Ty poskachesh' vo mrake, po beskrainim kholodnym kholmam," draft, [1962] (Box 67, Folder 1712)
      - "Ty smeeshsia chemu to vslukh na iskhode sna," draft, undated (Box 67, Folder 1713)
      - "Ty uznaesh' menia po pocherku. V nashem revnivom tsarstve," drafts, [1987] (Box 67, Folder 1714-1715)
      - Tzushima screen
        See: "Voskhodiashchee zheltoe solntse sledit kosymi"
      - U pamiatnika A.S. Pushkinu v Odesse, proof, 1994 (Box 67, Folder 1716)
      - Urok, by Wisława Szymborska, Russian translation by Brodsky, draft, 1971 (Box 67, Folder 1717)
      - "Usually aloof," draft, undated (Box 67, Folder 1718)
      - "U-u-u govorit cheloveku vozdukh," draft, undated (Box 67, Folder 1719)
      - V al'bom Natal'i Skavronskoi, draft, 1969 (Box 67, Folder 1720)
      - V Anglii (I-VII)
        - Russian language version, drafts, undated (Box 67, Folder 1721-1722)
        - English translation by Alan Myers, drafts, proofs and printed versions, 1978 (Box 67, Folder 1723-1726)
          See also: Odnomu tiranu
      - "V derevne Bog zhivet ne po uglam," draft, 1964 (Box 67, Folder 1727)
      - "V duiushchikh v etikh kraiakh sil'nykh vetrakh listva," draft, undated (Box 67, Folder 1728)
      - "V etoi komnate pakhlo triap'em i syroi vodoi," draft, [1986] (Box 67, Folder 1729)
      - V gorakh
        - Russian language version, proof, undated
        - English interlinear translation by unidentified translator, draft, 1995 (Box 67, Folder 1730)
      - V Italii
        - Russian language version, draft, 1984 or 1985 (Box 67, Folder 1731-1732)
        - English translation by Brodsky, draft, undated (Box 67, Folder 1733)
      - V Krakove, by Jerzy Harasymowicz, Russian translation by Brodsky, draft, undated (Box 67, Folder 1734)
        Includes a draft of Otkrytka Metsenatu, by Jerzy Harasymowicz, Russian translation by Brodsky.
      - "V neizvestnyi port Gurzuf," handmade bound volume, 1963 or 1964 (Box 67, Folder 1735-1736)
        A volume bound with string consisting of a poem about the adventures of Khan Iusuf and fifteen illustrations (colored pencil) by Brodsky. Includes a typescript of the poem. Likely made for Anastasia Tomashevskaia.
      - V okrestnostiakh Aleksandrii, English translation by Brodsky, draft and printed version, 1983, undated (Box 67, Folder 1737)
      - V okrestnostiakh Atlantidy, [1993] (Box 67, Folder 1738)
      - V Ozernom Kraiu
        - Russian language version, draft and printed version, 1974 (Box 67, Folder 1739)
        - English translation by George Kline, printed versions, 1976 (Box 67, Folder 1740-1741)
      - V Palange, draft
      - V rasputitsu, draft, 1964 (Box 68, Folder 1742)
      - V razgar kholodnoi voiny, drafts, [1994] (Box 68, Folder 1743)
      - V sleduiushchii vek, drafts, 1994 (Box 68, Folder 1744-1745)
      - "V starom kafe na ostrove ventiliator pod potolkom," drafts, undated (Box 68, Folder 1746)
      - "V tot vecher vozle nashego ognia," draft, [1962] (Box 68, Folder 1747)
      - "V vozdukhe -- sil'nyi moroz i khvoia," drafts, [1994] (Box 68, Folder 1748)
      - A valentine, drafts, undated (Box 68, Folder 1749)
      - Variation in V, drafts and proof, 1985 (Box 68, Folder 1750)
      - "Vecher v sadu. Golova bolit," draft, undated (Box 68, Folder 1751)
      - "Vek byl v kontse kontsov," draft, undated (Box 68, Folder 1752)
      - Venetian stanzas
        See: Venetsianskie strofy
      - Venetsianskie strofy (I-II)
        - Russian language version, drafts, [1982] (Box 68, Folder 1753-1754)
        - English translation by Jane Miller and Brodsky, drafts and proof, 1987-1988 (Box 68, Folder 1755)
        - Italian translation by Annelisa Alleva, printed version, undated (Box 68, Folder 1756)
        - Italian translation by unidentified translator, printed version, undated (Box 68, Folder 1757)
      - Venice: Lido
        See: Lido
      - Verses on the winter campaign 1980
        See: Stikhi o zimnei kampanii 1980-ogo goda
      - Vertumn
        - Russian language version, drafts and proof, [1990] (Box 68, Folder 1758-1759)
        - English translation by Brodsky, drafts, proofs and printed version, 1991 (Box 68, Folder 1760-1761)
      - Vertumnus
        See: Vertumn
      - Via Funari
        See:Na Via Funari
      - Vid s kholma
        - Russian version, drafts, [1992] (Box 68, Folder 1762-1763)
        - English translation by Alan Myers and Brodsky, drafts and printed version, undated (Box 68, Folder 1764-1765)
          Includes notes on the translation by Ann Kjellberg.
      - View from the hill
        See: Vid s kholma
      - View with a flood
        See: Peizazh s navodneniem
      - Visit Russia ("Our Russia's a country of birches"), draft
      - Vizantiiskoe, drafts, [1994] (Box 68, Folder 1766)
      - A voice from under the table, by Richard Wilbur, Russian translation by Brodsky
        See: Golos iz-pod stolom (A voice from under the table)
      - "Vorotish'sia na rodinu. Nu chto zh"
        - Russian language version, drafts, 1961 (Box 68, Folder 1767)
        - English translation by unidentified translator, draft, undated (Box 68, Folder 1768)
      - "Voskhodiashchee zheltoe solntse sledit kosymi"
        - Russian language version, printed version, undated (Box 68, Folder 1769)
        - English translation by Brodsky, drafts, undated (Box 68, Folder 1770)
      - "Voskresnu i vernus' v derevniu, v izbu," draft, undated (Box 68, Folder 1771)
      - Vospominanie, drafts, 1995 (Box 68, Folder 1772)
      - "Vot ia i snova pod etim bestsvetnym nebom,", drafts, [1990] (Box 68, Folder 1773-1774)
      - "Vremia podscheta tsypliat iastrebom; skird v tumane"
        - Russian language version, drafts, [1978] (Box 68, Folder 1775-1776)
        - English translation by Brodsky, draft and printed version, 1981, 1996 (Box 68, Folder 1777)
      - "Vse chuzhdo v dome novomu zhil'tsu"
        - Russian language version
        - English translation by Brodsky, draft, undated (Box 68, Folder 1778)
      - "Vsia, chto ty zdes' prochitaesh, ne somnevaisia byl"
        See: "Vzgliani na dereviannyi dom"
      - "Vtoroe Rozhdestvo na beregu"
        - Russian language version, drafts, 1971 (Box 68, Folder 1779)
        - English translation by George Kline, drafts, 1976, undated (Box 68, Folder 1780)
          Custodial History
          Includes a letter from Brodsky to Kline and notes by Brodsky on the translation.
      - "Vy snova vmeste. God," drafts, undated (Box 68, Folder 1781)
      - "Vyplyvaia iz gavani," draft, undated (Box 68, Folder 1782)
      - Vystuplenie v Sorbonne, drafts, 1989 (Box 68, Folder 1783-1784)
      - Vyzdoravlivaiushchemu volosiku, drafts, undated (Box 68, Folder 1785-1787)
      - "Vzgliani na dereviannyi dom," drafts, [1988?] (Box 68, Folder 1788-1790)
        The verso of one draft includes a draft of "Vsia, chto ty zdes' prochitaesh, ne somnevaisia byl."
      - Weather, drafts, 1995 (Box 68, Folder 1791)
        See also: Cabbage and carrot
      - "What is it, Walcott, that one hears" (occasional to Derek Walcott), drafts, 1990 (Box 68, Folder 1792)
      - "When a bomber drops its load," draft, undated (Box 68, Folder 1793)
      - "When asked of its origin," draft, undated (Box 68, Folder 1794)
      - When Ed and Jill
        See: "Mir sozdan byl iz smeshen'ia griazi, vody, ognia"
      - "When Slava lays down his big baton" (occasional to Mstislav Rostropovich), draft, undated (Box 68, Folder 1795-1796)
      - "When you are old and grey and can't," drafts, undated (Box 68, Folder 1797)
      - "Who cares in what language one says 'it rains'," draft, undated (Box 68, Folder 1798)
      - "Why couldn't his body avoid the bullet," drafts, undated (Box 68, Folder 1799)
      - The will, by John Donne
        See: Zaveshchanie (The will), by John Donne, Russian translation by Brodsky
      - "Yesterday was faked papers, journey by train, anxiety and arrival," draft, undated (Box 68, Folder 1800)
      - York: In memoriam W.H. Auden
      - "Za Savu, Dravu i Moravu," draft
      - Zagadka angelu, drafts, [1962], 1972 (Box 68, Folder 1801-1802)
        See also: Series I, Correspondence -- Ann Kjellberg Correspondence (August 1997)
        Includes a photocopy of variant lines for the final stanza. The original is enclosed in a letter from George Kline to Ann Kjellberg, filed in Series I, Correspondence -- Ann Kjellberg Correspondence (August 1997).
      - "Zakrichat i zakhlopochut petukhi"
        - Russian language version, printed version, undated (Box 68, Folder 1803)
        - English translation by Jonathan Brent, printed version, 1978 (Box 68, Folder 1804)
        - English translation by Richard McKane, draft, undated (Box 68, Folder 1805)
      - "Zamerzshii kisel'nyi bereg. Priachushchii v moloke"
        - Russian language version, drafts, 1985-1986 (Box 69, Folder 1806-1807)
        - English translation by Derek Walcott, printed version, 2000 (Box 69, Folder 1808)
      - Zaveshchanie (The will), by John Donne, Russian translation by Brodsky, draft, undated (Box 69, Folder 1809)
      - "Zdravstvui, izbushka," draft, undated (Box 69, Folder 1810)
      - Zhivotnye (Beasts), by Richard Wilbur, Russian translation by Brodsky, draft, undated (Box 69, Folder 1811)
      - Zhizn' v rasseiannom svete, drafts, [1987] (Box 69, Folder 1812)
      - "Zimniaia luna, zimniaia luna," draft, 1980? (Box 69, Folder 1813)
      - Zimniaia pochta, printed version, undated (Box 69, Folder 1814)
      - Zimniaia svad'ba
        - Russian language version, draft
        - English translation by Richard McKane, draft, undated (Box 69, Folder 1815)
      - Zimnim vecherom v Ialte, drafts, [1969] (Box 69, Folder 1816)
        See also: Series I, Correspondence -- General Correspondence -- Tomashevskaia, Zoia, Series XI, Papers of Others -- George Kline Papers -- Pages from Kathy Gibson's notebook and Series XI, Papers of Others -- Others -- Ramunas and Elmira Katilius family archive
      - Zimnim vecherom na senovale, draft, 1965 (Box 69, Folder 1817)
      - Zof'ia, printed version, 1978 (Box 69, Folder 1818)
      - Unidentified fragments of poems by Brodsky, drafts, undated (Box 69, Folder 1819-1831)
      - Unidentified poems of uncertain authorship, drafts, undated (Box 69, Folder 1832)
        Masha Vorobiov gave this material to Ann Kjellberg.
  - Prose
    Prose consists of holograph and typescript drafts, proofs, and printed versions of essays, introductions and afterwords, letters to editors, short fiction and collections of prose writing. While most material is original, there are some photocopies. Brodsky's prose writing chiefly consists of analysis of classical and contemporary poets. Among his most celebrated essays are "On Grief and Reason" (on Robert Frost), Watermark (reflections on the city of Venice), and the memoirs "Less than one" and "In a room and a half." Most of Brodsky's prose writing after 1974 is in English and (unlike his poetry) he generally did not translate it himself.
    Printed Collections are book-length collections of essays, all of which were published during Brodsky's lifetime by Farrar, Straus & Giroux. Individual Prose Writings are essays, introductions and afterwords, letters to editors and short fiction outside the context of a printed collection. Many of these essays appeared in serial publications such as Times Literary Supplement and New Yorker.
    Prose is organized under two headings: Printed Collections and Individual Prose Writings.
    - Printed Collections
      Arranged alphabetically by title.
      - Less than One (New York: Farrar, Straus & Giroux, 1986)
        - Proposal and table of contents, draft, undated (Box 70, Folder 1833)
        - Proofs, 1986 (Box 70, Folder 1834-1835)
          Includes "deleted essays."
        - Cover art and dust jacket, 1986 (Box 70, Folder 1836)
      - On Grief and Reason (New York: Farrar, Straus & Giroux, 1995)
        - Drafts, 1994-1995, undated (Box 70, Folder 1837-1841)
        - Drafts, 1994-1995, undated (Box 71, Folder 1842-1845)
        - Dead matter, undated (Box 71, Folder 1846)
        - Proofs, 1995 (Box 71, Folder 1847-1852)
        - Proofs, 1995 (Box 72, Folder 1853-1860)
        - Proofs, 1995 (Box 73, Folder 1861-1864)
        - Dust jacket, 1995
        - Erratum, undated (Box 73, Folder 1865)
      - Watermark
        - English language version (New York: Farrar, Straus & Giroux, 1992)
          - Notes, [1989] (Box 73, Folder 1866)
          - Drafts, 1989-1992, undated (Box 73, Folder 1867-1869)
          - Drafts, 1989-1992, undated (Box 74, Folder 1870)
          - Drafts, 1989-1992, undated (Box 75, Folder 1871-1880)
          - Proofs, 1991-1992 (Box 75, Folder 1881-1883)
          - Proofs, 1991-1992 (Box 76, Folder 1884-1887)
          - Dust jacket, 1992 (Box 76, Folder 1888)
        - Russian translation by G. Dashevskii, printed version, 1992 (Box 76, Folder 1889)
        - Russian translation by unidentified translator, fragment, draft, undated (Box 76, Folder 1890)
        - German translation by Jörg Trobitius, excerpt, printed version, 1991 (Box 76, Folder 1891)
        - Italian translation by Gilberto Forti, printed version, 1989 (Box 76, Folder 1892)
    - Individual prose writings
      Individual Prose Writings are further organized under four headings: Essays, Introductions and Afterwords to Others' Work, Letters to Editors, and Short Fiction. Essays are arranged alphabetically by title. Introductions to Others' Work are arranged alphabetically by the name of the author being introduced or by title (for volumes without a single author). Letters to Editors are arranged chronologically. Short fiction is arranged alphabetically by title.
      - Essays
        - "About one poem"
          See: "Ob odnom stikhotvorenii"
        - "After a journey"
          See: "Posle puteshestviia"
        - "Aktovaia rech'"
          See: "A commencement address"
        - "Altra ego"
          - English language version, drafts and printed versions, 1989-1990 (Box 77, Folder 1893-1900)
          - Russian translation by Irina Ninova, draft and printed version, 1991 (Box 77, Folder 1901)
          - Russian translation by Elena Kasatkina, drafts, 1997 (Box 77, Folder 1902-1903)
        - "Amnesty International", 1976? (Box 77, Folder 1904-1905)
        - "The art of Montale"
          See: "In the shadow of Dante"
        - "Beyond consolation"
          - Russian language version (untitled), draft, [1974] (Box 77, Folder 1906)
          - English translation by Barry Rubin, draft and printed version, 1974 (Box 77, Folder 1907)
        - "La Biennale," draft, undated (Box 77, Folder 1908)
        - "Blood, lies and the trigger of history," drafts and printed version, 1993 (Box 77, Folder 1909-1911)
        - "Boredom's uses"
          See: "In praise of boredom"
        - "Catastrophes in the air"
          - English language version, draft, 1984 (Box 77, Folder 1912-1913)
          - Russian translation by E. Maslova, draft, 1984 (Box 77, Folder 1914)
          - Russian translation by Andrei Levkin, draft, 1986 (Box 77, Folder 1915)
        - "A cat's meow," drafts and printed version, 1992-1993 (Box 77, Folder 1916-1919)
        - "The child of civilization"
          - English language version, draft and printed versions, 1977 (Box 77, Folder 1920-1921)
          - English language version, draft and printed versions, 1977 (Box 78, Folder 1922)
          - Russian translation by Valentina Polukhina, draft and printed version, 1982 (Box 79, Folder 1923-1924)
        - "Chto proizoshlo v Pol'she," printed version, 1982 (Box 79, Folder 1925)
        - "Collector's item"
          - English language version, drafts and printed versions, 1991-1994 (Box 79, Folder 1926-1934)
          - Russian translation by Aleksandr Sumerkin, drafts, circa 1994 (Box 79, Folder 1935-1936)
        - "A commencement address"
          Based on an address at Williams College.
          - English language version, draft and printed version, 1984 (Box 79, Folder 1937)
          - Russian translation by unidentified translator, draft, undated (Box 79, Folder 1938)
          - Russian translation by A.Z. Kolotov, draft, 1988 (Box 79, Folder 1939)
        - "The condition we call 'exile'," drafts and printed version, 1987-1988 (Box 79, Folder 1940-1942)
          Printed version includes commentary from participants at the Wheatland Foundation Conference in Vienna, 1987.
        - "Conspiracy of silence," drafts and proof, 1987 (Box 79, Folder 1943)
        - "Dan' Marku Avreliiu"
          See: "Homage to Marcus Aurelius"
        - "Dido and Aeneas," drafts, 1995 (Box 80, Folder 1944-1945)
        - "Does the poet have an obligation to society?," draft, 1991, undated (Box 80, Folder 1946)
        - "Emigration in the 1970s," draft (Box 80, Folder 1947-1949)
        - "Eve, Lilith, woman and poetic creation," drafts, 1986-1991 (Box 80, Folder 1950-1951)
        - "The fate of a poetess..." (on Natalia Gorbanevskaia), English translation by Carl Proffer, draft and printed version, 1972 (Box 80, Folder 1952)
        - "Flight from Byzantium"
          See: "Puteshestvie v Stambul"
        - "A footnote to a commentary"
          See: "Primechaniia k kommentariiu"
        - "Footnote to a poem"
        - "For whom the crumbling belfry tolls," drafts, proof and printed version, 1991-1993 (Box 80, Folder 1953)
        - "Gemini at large," draft, 1992 (Box 80, Folder 1954)
        - "Gennady Smakov, 48, translator and author" (obituary), drafts and printed version, 1988 (Box 80, Folder 1955)
        - "Geografiia zla" (review of The Gulag Archipelago and other writings by Aleksandr Solzhenitsyn)
          - Russian language version, draft and printed version, 1977, 1999 (Box 80, Folder 1956-1957)
          - English translation by Barry Rubin, drafts and printed version, 1977 (Box 80, Folder 1958-1959)
        - "The Geography of Evil"
          See: "Geografiia zla"
        - "Glazami chastitsy" (review of Opasnye mysli by Iurii Orlov), draft, undated (Box 80, Folder 1960)
        - "A great Russian poet's guide to Leningrad"
          See: "A guide to a renamed city"
        - "A guide to a renamed city"
          - English language version, draft and printed version, 1979 (Box 80, Folder 1961)
          - Russian translation by A.Z. Kolotov, draft, 1988 (Box 80, Folder 1962)
        - "Happy birthday to you"
          See: "Razmyshlenie ob ischadii ada"
        - "He refused to work for the KGB," draft, 1979 (Box 80, Folder 1963)
        - "A hidden duet"
        - "Homage to Marcus Aurelius"
          - English language version, drafts, proof and printed version, 1993-1994 (Box 80, Folder 1964-1968)
          - English language version, drafts, proof and printed version, 1993-1994 (Box 81, Folder 1969-1972)
          - Russian translation by Viktor Golyshev, draft, 1995 (Box 81, Folder 1973)
          - Spanish translation by Marco Aurelio Major, printed version, 1995 (Box 81, Folder 1974)
        - "Homage to vertebrae"
        - "How to read a book"
          - English language version, drafts, 1988-1991 (Box 81, Folder 1975-1978)
          - Russian translation by [Elena Kasatkina], draft, undated (Box 81, Folder 1979)
        - "An immodest proposal," drafts and printed version, 1991 (Box 81, Folder 1980-1982)
        - "In a room and a half"
          - English language version, drafts, proof and printed version, 1986, undated (Box 81, Folder 1983-1987)
          - Russian translation by A.Z. Kolotov, draft, 1988 (Box 81, Folder 1988)
          - Serbian translation by Ljubitsa Strnchević, printed version, 1986 (Box 81, Folder 1989)
        - "In memory of Stephen Spender," drafts and proof, 1995 (Box 81, Folder 1990-1993)
        - "In memory of Stephen Spender," draft, 1995 (Box 82, Folder 1994)
        - "In praise of boredom"
          See also: Series I, Correspondence -- General Correspondence -- Harper's Magazine
          Based on an address at Dartmouth College.
          - English language version, drafts and printed version, 1989, 1996 (Box 83, Folder 1995-1998)
          - Russian translation by [Elena Kasatkina], draft, 1989 (Box 83, Folder 1999)
        - "In praise of gray," draft, 1990 (Box 83, Folder 2000)
        - "In the shadow of Dante"
          - English language version, draft and printed versions, 1977, undated (Box 83, Folder 2001)
          - Russian translation by Elena Kasatkina, draft and printed version, 1986 (Box 83, Folder 2002)
        - "Isaiah Berlin at eighty," drafts and printed version, 1989-1991, undated (Box 83, Folder 2003-2005)
        - "Journey to Istanbul"
        - "Kak byt' levym v Amerike," draft, undated (Box 83, Folder 2006)
        - "Kak chitat' knigu"
          See: "How to read a book"
        - "Katastrofy v vozdukhe"
          See: "Catastrophes in the air"
        - "The keening muse"
          - Drafts and printed version, 1982 (Box 83, Folder 2007-2009)
          - Russian translation by A.Z. Kolotov, draft, 1988 (Box 83, Folder 2010)
          - Russian translation by M. Temkina, draft and printed version, 1986 (Box 83, Folder 2011-2012)
          - French translation by Laurence Dyevre, draft, undated (Box 83, Folder 2013)
        - "Kollektsionnyi ekzempliar"
          See: "Collector's item"
        - "Learning English", draft, undated (Box 83, Folder 2014)
        - "Less than one"
          - English language version, draft and printed version, 1979 (Box 83, Folder 2015-2018)
          - Russian translation by unidentified translator, fragment of draft and proof, undated (Box 83, Folder 2019)
        - "Letter to Horace," drafts and printed version, 1995, undated (Box 83, Folder 2020-2021)
        - "Letter to Horace," drafts and printed version, 1995, undated (Box 84, Folder 2022-2028)
        - "Letter to a President"
          - English language version, drafts and printed versions, 1993 (Box 84, Folder 2029-2030)
          - Russian translation by [Elena Kasatkina], draft, circa 1996 (Box 84, Folder 2031)